Guide to the Pacific Slope Scrapbooks, 1819-1906
Department of Special Collections
Pacific Slope Scrapbooks,
1819-1906
Special Collections M0211
Barnes, Mary Sheldon
25 volumes
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Provenance:
Collected by Mary Shelden Barnes and other Stanford faculty and students.
Acquisition Information:
Unknown
Access Restrictions
None.
Scope and Contents Note:
This collection has three series: scrapbooks on San Francisco and California, Pacific Slope History scrapbooks, and Pacific Slope pamphlets. Volumes in the first series contain clippings from 1855 to 1894 pertaining to political and civic issues, railroads, and the general history of San Francisco and California. The Pacific Slope History scrapbooks in series 2 contain clippings, with some letters and other documents, pertaining to Indians (1880s-1890s); Alaska, Pacific, and Asiatic relations (1860s-1890s); Oregon Country (1846 and later); the San Francisco Peninsula (1890s); and the 1906 San Francisco earthquake.
CONTAINER LIST
- Scrapbooks on San Francisco and California
  - General clippings, 1855-1864 (Othercontainertype 1)
  - Clippings primarily on railroads, 1872-1875 (Othercontainertype 2)
  - General clippings, 1873-1874 (Othercontainertype 3)
  - General clippings, 1875-1877 (Othercontainertype 4)
  - General clippings, 1883-1885 (Othercontainertype 5)
  - Clippings mounted in manuscript diary by Washington Bartlett, 1884 (Othercontainertype 6)
  - Clippings on political and civic issues, 1885 (Othercontainertype 7)
  - General clippings, 1885-1886 (Othercontainertype 8)
  - Clippings on political and civic issues, 1886 (Othercontainertype 9)
  - General clippings, 1887-1894 (Othercontainertype 10)
- Pacific Slope History Scrapbooks
  - Indians (Othercontainertype 1)
    Clippings on Indians are arranged by subject spanning the period of the 1880s and 1890s. Items of note include:
    p. 6: letter by Ambrose Bierce on spearheads, 1892 June 19
    p. 17: letter of M. W. Greer to Mrs. Barnes, 1893 May 9
    p. 19: letter of L. C. G. Harris to Mrs. Barnes, 1892 May 30
    p. 94: manuscript copy of a speech of Standing Bear
    p. 122: manuscript note signed by Margaret Hood
  - General History (Othercontainertype 2)
    Clippings in this volume date from 1819 to 1846. Items of note include:
    p. 2: telegram from N. P. Vallejo to Wm. Boggs on the death of his father, 1890 Jan. 19
    p. 3: letter from W. M. Boggs to Mrs. Barnes on the Boggs -Boone relationship, 1892 Dec. 17
    p. 6: letter from W. M. Boggs to Mrs. Barnes on the Donner Party and Mrs. Kelsey, 1893 Feb 5
  - General History (Othercontainertype 3)
    This volume of clippings begins in 1846 and includes, on page 105, a manuscript poem, "Song of the Iron Horse."
  - California Civil War Period (Othercontainertype 4)
    This volume of clippings on California during the Civil War begins in 1850. Items of note include:
    p. 1: "A Constitution for the Overland Journey Contributed by A. R. Cotton;" typescript
    p. 2: letter from John Brown Jr., sec. San Bernadino Society of California Pioneers, to Benjamin R. Bledsoe concerning pioneer songs
    p. 10: letter from W. M. Boggs to Mrs. Barnes concerning flour prices, 1892 Dec. 16
    p. 21: note from P. Scanlon to Mayor Bartlett giving entry to the Alms House, 1885
    p. 81: certificate concerning railroad fare signed by E. P. Marselein, Society of California Pioneers
  - Oregon Country (Othercontainertype 5)
    This volume contains clippings, 1846 and later, about the area that became the states of Oregon, Washington, and Idaho. Also included on pages 11-12 is a manuscript of the song "Oregon" as recalled by Henry Hill.
  - Alaska, Pacific and Asiatic Relations (Othercontainertype 6)
    This volume contains clippings pertaining to Alaska, the Sandwich Islands, China, Japan, and other Pacific and Asian relations, 1860s-1890s. Of note on page 37 is a letter from U. Thompson to Mrs. Barnes concerning Hawaiians, 1893 Mar. 27.
  - San Francisco Peninsula (Othercontainertype 7)
    This volume of clippings pertains to the general history of the San Francisco peninsula in the 1890s. Also included is a printed circular letter of the Law and Order League of California.
  - 1906 San Francisco Earthquake and Fire (Othercontainertype 7a)
    This volume was assembled by G. A. Batchelder and, in addition to clippings, includes telegrams and letters on pages 1-4, 94-95, and 125.
- Pacific Slope Pamphlets
  This series consists of seven volumes of pamphlets pertaining to the Pacific Slope. Of note in volume 3 are the following:
  "The Sun God; an Indian Edda," by J. E. Wharton. Phoenix, Arizona, 1889; typescript, with a letter from J. E. Wharton to Mary S. Barnes, 1893 Mar. 6
  "Indian reluctance to talk about religion or superstition"